Guide to the Papers of Ethel Thomas Herold M1991
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Ethel Thomas Herold papers
1896-2001
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Herold, Elmer
Herold, Ethel Thomas
M1991
4.5 Linear Feet 5 manuscript boxes, 2 flat boxes
Correspondence, diaries, interview transcripts, and other material related to Ethel Thomas Herold and Elmer Herold, who lived and taught in the Philippines for 37 years beginning in 1922. For three of those years the Herolds were held in Japanese internment camp called Camp Holmes during World War II. They witnessed the Philippines change from being a colony to an independent nation. There is also material concerning Betty Halsema Foley and Jim Halsema, the latter a journalist with the Herolds in the internment camp.
Scope and Contents
The papers include correspondence (from both Ethel and Elmer), a transcript of Ethel's experiences during World War II as told to Charles Vial, Ethel's World War II diary, and material relating to Betty Halsema Foley and Jim Halsema, the latter a journalist with the Herolds in the internment camp (Camp Holmes). In addition there are four volumes of The Ariel, 1915-1918, a yearbook published by the junior class of Lawrence College (Appleton, Wisconsin).
Biographical / Historical
Ethel Thomas Herold grew up in small-town Wisconsin, married her college sweet-heart, Elmer, and both followed her brother to teach in the Philippines in 1922. There, with but a couple of brief interruptions, she spent the next thirty-seven years, including three in a Japanese internment camp during World War II. They witnessed the Philippines change from being a colony to an independent nation.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given by Betsy Herold Heimke to Stanford University, Special Collections in 2013.
Access to Collection
Open for research; material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Philippines -- History -- 1898-1946 -- Personal narratives.; Women -- Philippines.; Diaries.; Philippines -- History -- 1946-1986 -- Sources.; Americans -- Philippines -- Sources.; Herold, Elmer; Lawrence College (Appleton, Wis.); Foley, Betty Halsema; Halsema, James J.; Herold, Ethel Thomas; Holmes Internment Camp (Baguio, Philippines); Vial, Charles
- Experiences of Ethel Thomas Herold During World War II in the Philippines as told for Charles Vial and recorded by William Herold (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Camp Holmes, Ethel Herold (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Ethel Herold Correspondence, 1946-2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Herold Outgoing Correspondence, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Elmer Herold Correspondence and various articles, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Incoming Correspondence, 1946-1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence from Ethel Herold to Betsy, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence from Ethel Herold to Betsy, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence from Ethel Herold, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence from Ethel Herold to Betsy and Karl Heimki, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence from Ethel Herold to Betsy and Karl Heimki, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence from Ethel Herold to Betsy and Karl Heimke, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence from Ethel Herold to Betsy, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence from Ethel Herold, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence from Ethel Thomas, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence from Ethel Herold, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence from Ethel Herold, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence from Ethel Herold, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence from Ethel Herold, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence from Ethel Herold, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, Miscellaneous, 1963-1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Correspondence from Ethel Herold, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Miscellaneous Material (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Mother's letters, 1980-10 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- World War II Diary December 8, 1941 - May 9, 1945, 1941-1945 (Box 3, Folders 3-5)
- Jim Halsema, 2001-05-01 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Jim Halsema's Reconstituted Diary Jan. 4, 1943 - Nov. 21, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Various Manuscripts (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Various Manuscripts (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Foley, Betty Fundraiser for Charities, 1997-08-14 (Box 4, Folders 2-4)
- Overland Parks, Kansas, 1972-09-29 (Box 4, Folders 5-11, Box 5, Folder 1)
- Bulletin of the American Historical Collection (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Bureau of Education Student's Note Book (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Ethel letters, Etc., 1949-1970 (Box 5, Folders 4-5)
- Miscellaneous Material (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous Material (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Miscellaneous Material (Box 5, Folder 8)
- The Ariel, 1915 (Flat-box 6, Volume 1)
- Lawrence College of Wisconsin (Flat-box 6, Volume 2)
- The Ariel 18 (Flat-box 7, Volume 1)
- The Ariel, 1917 (Flat-box 7, Volume 2)